The Japanese government, working through
the Bank of Japan, just lit $35 billion
on fire and then flushed it down the
toilet. And if that wasn't enough,
officials in Tokyo are talking about
embarrassing themselves even further in
the oil market. After wasting 5 and 1/2
trillion yen,
why not throw some more money down the
hole for nothing more than the public
spectacle of it? What a world we live
in. Unfortunately for them and their
counterparts in India, it's the
Eurodollar's world and we're all just
along for the ride. Now, I'm talking
about currency market interventions.
After weeks of, yes, speculation about
whether the government in Japan would go
after speculation in FX markets,
it's pretty clear they did on Thursday.
But that wasn't enough, nor is it ever
going to be. Not to be deterred, now the
Japanese are talking about taking their
puppet show to the oil futures market
because, let's face reality, that's the
problem, the real one. I've been telling
you from the beginning, energy shock
equals dollar shock, which is a
Eurodollar matter, not something about
speculators. These are fundamental
monetary problems. And if nothing else,
the Japanese should be in touch with
their counterparts in India. The Indians
just disclosed a massive, record short
dollar position and guess what that did
for the rupee. The same thing it always
does. Governments don't actually control
anything. We're just told, repeatedly,
that they do. In fact, it's the fairy
tale that's actually the policy. You got
to see the truth here.
If you believe the big bad bureaucrat
holds all the cards, then you'll fold
out of the game and get out of the way.
But that's not how the world works, the
Eurodollar's world. We don't have a
confidence problem, it's a real money,
real economy one that's getting really
uncomfortable for a hell of a lot more
than just rupees and yen.
Now, for the Japanese, though, whenever
they get close to intervention, they
usually start out with the typical
statements about, you know, one-sided
trading, how the yen isn't behaving
according to fundamentals as they define
the fundamentals. The Finance Ministry
has a bureaucratic list of what
constitutes basically every one of these
parameters that are usually tied to
completely irrelevant factors. And then
the warnings get even more pointed. And
this time that was absolutely the case.
In fact, the Finance Minister herself,
Satsuki Katayama, started warning about
reporters making sure they had their
phones with them. Quote, "Please keep
your smartphones with you at all times,
whether you're going out or resting."
That's what she said just before the
holiday started. And sure enough,
suddenly the yen popped on Thursday.
That's because despite all the warnings
and talking, the the posturing
beforehand, JPY had sunk to nearly 161
in early trading, basically forcing the
government to do something. When the yen
jumped to around 155, which is a pretty
sizable bounce back, it was pretty clear
why that had been. Officials haven't
confirmed that they were in the FX
market, but it's obvious that's what
happened. First of all, Japan's top
currency official, Atsushi Mimura, said,
quote, "Let me say this is my final
advisory if you want to escape." And
that was early Thursday morning. And
then he said something to the effect
that the Japanese had already been in
contact with the US Treasury, hadn't
gotten any pushback of effectively
green-lighting an intervention, if
indeed there was one. And there was. We
know there was. Using data from
government accounts and comparing them
to forecasts that are made by brokers,
you get a sense of you get a really good
sense of how much reserves might have
been used or, you know, how much money
the Japanese government just basically
flushed down the toilet. And it was
roughly 5.4 trillion, or the US dollar
equivalent of 34 and 1/2 billion. Just
lit it on fire, tossed it into the
dumpster. Then again, from Tokyo's
perspective, what else can they do?
Japan is in a very tough spot. You have
to understand what the government is
trying to accomplish here. They're not
really trying to strengthen the yen
necessarily, but to stabilize it.
Authorities have clearly decided that
160 to the dollar is their red line. So,
every time JPY drops around 160, the
government comes out with something,
doesn't matter what it is, trying to
shoo it back away from that level. Not
to reverse the currency's trajectory,
but to keep it from going lower and
possibly a lot lower. But, contrary to
the nonsense you hear from the
mainstream, yen weakness isn't about
what everybody says it is. They always
say it's about interest rates. I mean,
that's all you ever hear. US dollar
rates are higher than yen rates, and
even as the latter have been moving
sharply upward for the past year and
closing the gap,
despite all the rate hikes, despite the
rising JGB yields, the yen is weaker now
than what it had been back when Japanese
policy rates were negative alongside
most government bond yields. It's not
interest rates.
That's not why the yen was weak. And
I've gone over this many times over the
years. Interest rates are not why JPY
continues to want to move lower. And
it's especially true right now with oil
prices. That's why they feel they have
to make these big, bold statements. It's
not about money. For them, it's about
psychology. And like central banks,
they're just as bad at it because it's a
losing proposition from the start. This
is the euro dollar's world, not
government. All right, quick shout out
to today's video sponsor, Monarch.
Monarch is a financial tool that's worth
knowing because it's a cleaner way to
see your money. It is basically a
private, ad-free dashboard that pulls
together all your credit cards, your
bank statements, your investments, and
puts it all into one place. The whole
point is to be clear on your money
without turning it into some kind of
stressful project. So, here's how it
works. You open one screen and you can
see your spending, your net worth, your
trends over time, even recurring bills.
So, you're not jumping between five
different apps trying to piece it all
together. What I like about how it's
built is that it's not trying to nag
you. Instead of micromanaging every
transaction, it gets it gives you this
clean picture of where your money
actually goes. It's also read-only
encrypted, so it's tracking and
planning, not touching your accounts.
This is the kind of thing that makes
sense for a monthly check-in, a net
worth review, or just I mean, if you're
just kind of figuring out or trying to
figure out where your money's leaking
without turning budgeting into some kind
of like second job. And if you manage
your money with a partner, you can share
the same view, the same goals, the same
bills, all with fewer surprises. Let me
tell you this, too. Monarch has a
4.9-star rating, and it works with over
13,000 financial institutions, and
again, private, ad-free.
So, if you want the clarity without the
chaos, and let's face it, we all need a
little bit of financial clarity, there's
a link on the screen for you to follow.
Now, this part is really easy. You got
to buy oil, which means you got to have
dollars. And when oil prices go way up,
and you have to buy a lot more oil than
you were expecting because the oil that
you contracted for didn't show up,
you're going to need a lot more dollars,
and that's going to drive the price of
dollars up, and therefore, your own
currency down much lower. Interest rates
don't really factor here, except one
other expense to factor in as you
desperately try to seek out eurodollar
funding.
It really is that simple, but the
mainstream has been conditioned to
instead couch everything in terms of
interest rate because central banks,
which by the way, aren't really central
banks, they need interest rates to be at
the center of everything because
interest rate policy is all these quasi
central banks have. It's their only
tool. Therefore, they need you they need
you and me to believe it fixes
everything. Except with Japan and the
yen, it doesn't fix anything. Rates have
been going up, JPY keeps going down
anyway. That was true before the latest
oil spike, but when the energy shock
showed up, this connection became even
clearer than it had been before. If you
didn't see it prior to March,
you don't have any choice to look away
right now. Quote,
the correlation between dollar yen and
Brent crude rose to its highest level
since late 2021, a day before Japanese
authorities intervened in the currency
market, at least unofficially intervened
in the currency market, underscoring the
tighter link between oil prices and the
yen. While the wide interest rate gap
between the US and Japan has long been
cited as a key factor behind yen
weakness, and it's just not true, the
recent surge in oil prices tied to
Middle East tensions is seen as another
important driver. Not another Not
another important It is the driver.
Basic euro dollar mechanics. Because of
this, get this, the government in Tokyo
is now talking about intervening. No,
not just in FX. They've already done
that. Very likely have done that.
They're talking about intervening in the
oil market. So, let's go back to the
article here.
Japanese officials have also begun to
scrutinize speculative trading. They
always blame the speculator. Speculative
trading in crude oil futures, saying
it's become a new factor driving
currency moves. Top currency official,
there's that guy again, Atsushi Mimura,
said on Friday that authorities are
maintaining readiness to intervene in
the crude oil futures market. Again,
Japan is in a bind, so you can see to a
certain extent where they're coming
from. They've got a monetary problem,
they've got economic problems, and as
the currency goes lower, it makes all of
those problems even worse. And as oil
continues to go higher,
what are they going to do? They can't
just sit there and do nothing. So, you
do have a little bit of sympathy for
their position. It's the other parts,
the constant lying, the constant hyping
about factors that don't really matter.
That's really where we have issue.
So, think about it this way. The country
gets an estimated 90% of its oil
imported from the Middle East, and a lot
of that is still flowing, but a big
chunk obviously isn't. So, they're
getting hit two ways, missing physical
product as well as dramatically higher
prices. Now, to the former, the
government has already released about 80
million barrels from the strategic
reserves, but but as this energy shock
drags on, the strains are only going to
get worse and prices are only going to
go even higher. So, those measures not
going to be nearly enough. So, again,
you can understand the idea of
intervening in the oil market, trying to
get prices there to go down, therefore
alleviating some of the pressure on the
currency.
But that's what this mostly is, more
jawboning and talk, hoping to scare away
speculators. Except, just like with JPY,
Japan's problems aren't really
speculation. This is real-world
commodities and real money, real euro
dollars, well, okay, virtual ledger euro
dollars, but in reality, they're needed
to pay for it. So, if they were going to
intervene oil, if they actually were
going to intervene in oil, that would
mean shorting in oil futures. They're
not going to suddenly sell all the
reserves to flood the market for a day
or two. No, they're going to move on the
so-called paper market, the futures
market. That's the idea, anyway. I mean,
think about it this way, too. President
Trump has been doing this all along, and
we've talked about the differences
between the futures price and the cash
price. The paper price, which is
futures, has definitely responded, not
to threats of manipulation in the US
case or Trump's case,
in his it's it's reacting to reacting
harshly to the possibility the next
Truth Social that talks about how close
the UN the US and Iran are to coming up
with a deal. You know, every time
something comes out from President
Trump, the paper price of oil therefore
drops. Now, the Japanese, they're going
to produce the same effect, but instead
resorting to threats about taking on
speculative positions of their own.
That's how stupid this really is. To
fight the speculators,
Japan is going to have to out-speculate
them.
Now, assuming that's where this goes,
how do you think that would go?
Government bureaucrats checking their
approved list, conducting committee
meetings about which contracts to buy to
make sure the trades are spread out
fairly among the various banks, and
one reason why official interventions
never really work, at least of all
because it's officials who are
intervening. Now, according to reports,
the finance ministry had already
contacted banks and traders back in
March. So, you have to wonder why they
didn't do anything since then, and
probably because it's not really
feasible. So, again, the real goal here
is to try to jawbone market traders,
make threats that you're going to short
the hell out of the paper price of oil,
trying to scare away every last leverage
long speculator. But, Asia doesn't need
speculators for high prices and huge
spreads. It was an honest-to-goodness
shortage, one that is getting bigger,
and it's going to start running into
hard limits. Thus, prices are indeed
behaving fundamentally.
Now, the Japanese haven't intervened in
FX markets for 2 years. Late April
heading into the holiday, yen screaming
toward 160, this should sound very
familiar. At the time, they took about
10 trillion yen and lit it on fire and
flushed it down the toilet because it
didn't really work.
Yen kept going lower right on into July.
And one key reason why that had been?
The last oil shock. We've talked about
this repeatedly. As the global economy
fell off in early 2024, the global pivot
around March and April 2024, that
falling demand eventually had an effect
on crude prices, sending them on a
downward slide even before Tokyo flushed
its 10 trillion down the toilet. And
even the decline in oil prices, that
wasn't what quote saved the yen in 2024.
Instead, as economic weakness triggered
broader concerns, Japanese carry traders
reversed their carry trades. The carry
traders reversed their carry trades
starting in the middle of July and
leading to the blowup in early August.
And that reversal, among other things,
pushed the yen sharply higher in a way
the Japanese government could only have
dreamed of. But, once the carry trade
volatility died down, JPY was moving
back lower again. Only due to the same
thing starting in January 2025, the
so-called tariff volatility early last
year put Japanese carry traders in mind
to reverse more of their trades sending
JPY soaring higher and in doing so
provoked some of that, you know, sell
America dollar doom nonsense out of
people who have no clue about the yen
dollar's doom or even America for that
matter. But once that carry trade
reversal, the second one, reversed later
in April 2025, look what JPY has done
ever since. Lower and lower and lower.
The 2024 interventions didn't do
anything just like the 2022
interventions hadn't either. In that
case, the yen was, quote, saved once
again temporarily that time by China's
reopening which sparked for a little
while some hope that the global economy
was going to be able to turn around from
that Chinese resurgence. Except as we
know, and we knew that from the very
beginning, there was no Chinese
resurgence. And the only things which
did turn around were all those
previously hopeful reflationary trades
like the yen going higher.
Governments always fail, so government
interventions do too. Yet the media
constantly talks about official policies
and actions like they are the only
things that matter.
They make central banks in particular
seem like they have to be central when
in fact these quasi central banks aren't
central to anything other than a fairy
tale and media spun narrative. This is
the euro dollar's world and right now
the euro dollar is agitated by a whole
bunch of factors starting with recently
the energy shock producing the dollar
shock. That's the fundamental reality
that Japan and India are trying to deal
with.
Yes, so the poster child for everything
for getting repeatedly exposed as
insignificant, that's the Reserve Bank
of India. Central bankers do love two
things. First, the unearned media
attention they're slobbered with, and
second, embarrassing themselves trying
to get it. Now, RBI has been intervening
in FX for years, and what has it gotten
officials, India, or the rupee?
Absolutely nothing. It's all just noise,
pure unadulterated distraction. The most
that you can argue is that the Indian
rupee would have fallen farther and
faster if RBI had done nothing, which
should sound familiar. You'll recognize
it as the same stupid job save
counterfactual that can neither be
proven or as intended by economists
disproven. It's used in every single one
of their fade failed policies from zero
interest rates to QE. They say their
policies absolutely do work because the
world didn't end. It's complete crap.
And all you have to do is take a look at
the rupee, and you don't even you don't
even need to know when the interventions
happened. Just know that they were there
repeatedly, and yet the trend for INR
doesn't seem to have noticed any single
one of them. More recently, sure enough,
the Reserve Bank has been totally busy.
After all, if you want to justify your
job and appear to be relevant, but you
can't actually achieve anything close to
your goals, next best thing is just to
appear appear very busy. Leverage the
media, making it sound really big and
important, and hope no one really
notices the difference. And you can be
sure the stock market won't notice
because the stock market loves this
idea, the fantasy of a powerful central
bank. But the real markets,
not so much. Quote, "The Indian Central
Bank's intervention in the derivatives
market rose sharply in March, with its
net short dollar position surging to a
record 103 billion." Net short dollar
positions rose 25 billion from February,
so just March alone, according to
Bloomberg calculations based on Reserve
Bank of India data that was released
this past week. The data, which is a
reflection of the RBI's intervention in
both onshore and offshore
non-deliverable forwards markets, rose
as the authority intensified its defense
of the currency in the midst of surging
crude prices following the US-Iran war.
And officials had previously done big
things not really that long ago,
including limiting local Indian banks to
just a hundred million dollars for their
open FX trading positions. And even
though the banks put up a big stink
about it, and the media went nuts over
how this was a huge thing, biggest thing
in more than a decade, guess what? The
rupee reversed only for a short time
before resuming its slide all over
again. And on Friday, another record low
at 95 to the dollar. So, lots of media
coverage, lots of oohing and aahing over
the big numbers, the heavy hand of
macroprudential policy with absolutely
nothing to show for it. Why? Same story
as Japan. Eurodollar fundamentals and
basic small-e economics. Energy shock
creates a dollar shock.
Now, the other part of this is the part
no one wants to talk about. You're not
supposed to talk about this. Dollar
demand, that's easy, pretty clear,
visible, straightforward. Need dollars
for oil, oil goes up, dollar demand goes
way up. But what about the supply side?
But no one ever talks about the supply
of dollars because once you start
digging in on that side, you uncover a
whole lot of things you never expected,
including why I repeatedly call central
banks pseudo central banks. We're
supposed to believe that since these are
dollars, we've been talking about this
entire video, the Federal Reserve
printed trillions of them, so there
couldn't possibly be a problem with
money supply, dollar supply. Now, first
off, supply is never really the issue,
it's always circulation. Second, what's
being circulated has almost nothing to
do with the Fed and its bank reserves.
And even if the Fed's bank reserves did
circulate outside the domestic US
banking system, it still wouldn't matter
because what does is the condition of
commercial banks operating this euro
dollar world. And they do not like where
it is heading. They didn't like it long
before the Iran conflict and the energy
shock. I mean, after all, cockroaches
and private credit, which is a global
problem. Hell, the Japanese carry
traders, they're euro dollar providers
and they stopped recirculating as many
euro dollars back in the summer
because they correctly saw the future in
global flat beverage as well as what
that would do to those very credit
markets. In other words, the Japanese
and the Indians, as far as government
officials, aren't just facing dollar
demand to pay for more expensive, harder
to get oil. They're having to do so at
the same time those with dollars don't
want to part with them in the same way
that they had at the same previously
reasonable prices. So, sharply lower
currency rates reflect both sides of the
euro dollar equation. And there is
nothing governments can do about this,
same as it has been for decades. Sorry
you never got the memo because none of
those governments ever sent it. They
don't want you to know because it
exposes just how powerless they are.
But hey, the Japanese aren't just going
to intervene in yen, they're going to
intervene in the oil market, too,
because why the hell not?
It's all just fiction and fairy tale.
It's all just for public consumption.
It's all to maintain an illusion
that this is not the euro dollar's
world. But it has been the euro dollar's
world for a very, very, very long time
and these interventions are going to do
one thing, and that's to further prove
that's been the case.
If you want to talk about the banks have
been up to in the euro dollar world,
let's talk about what European banks are
doing locally in Europe and therefore
what they're doing beyond Europe. That's
all in the video link below. As always,
thank you very much for joining me. Huge
thank you Euro dollar University members
and subscribers and until next time,
take care.